中英字幕by:Ocean-藏心(微博)    推荐指数:★★★★
简介: 视频短小精悍,12分钟讲通了自定义视图的方方面面
用自定义视图来增强AndroidUI
Enhancing Android UI with Custom Views
我是大卫 史密斯
Hello,I am David Smith
我是一个Android开发的头头,在Double Encore这家公司
An Android dev lead on  Double Encore
还是在NewCircle的Android讲师
and an Android Instructor here at NewCircle
今天我准备带你领略
Today,I am going to walk you through the process
Android里面自定义View以及ViewGroup的过程
building custom views and view groups on Android
作为开发者,写自定义控件
As Developers,building custom view components is
是你能够欣然接受创意性UI设计的必备条件之一.
a necessary part of  embracing creative ui design
我们不应对设计师的天马行空感到恐惧
we shouldn't afraid to implement designer's unique vision
不应把问题归咎于framework或者
just because the framework
社区
or the community
没有提供现成的组件
doesn't provider a component that
帮我们来干这活
will do the job for us out the  box
卷起你的袖子把,骚年
getting our hands dirty
在这方面, 有很赞的方法来搞很赞的App
in this area,this is a great way to build great apps
自定义的图标控件
there are many great advantages
会有相当多的益处
to building your own icon components
例如说,你可以全权控制
such as the ability to have full control of
你的控件如何显示
how your content is displayed
但是,写自定义控件最重要的一点在于,
but one of the best reasons
to become an expert custom view creation
可以使你的视图层级结构平面化
is the ability to flatten your view hierarchy.
如果设计的好的话
one custom view
framework用多个控件镶嵌才能搞定的
可以一步到位由一个自定义控件来搞定.
can be designed do the job of several nested framework widgets.
你的视图层级结构里面的视图越少
and the fewer of views you have in your hierarchy
你的程序性能越好
the better your application perform
我们的第一个例子是写一个简单的控件,
our first example will be a simple widget
可以显示两张重叠的图片logos,
that displays a pair of overlapping image logos
文本部分显示在图片的右边,且居中于垂直方向
with the text element on the right in vertically center
例如,你可以利用一个像这样的控件
you might use a widget like this
来显示一场运动比赛的比分
to represent  the score of sport match for example
在我们写自定义控件时,
when we build custom views
有两个重要的函数,
there are two primary functions
我们必须了解知道
that we must take into consideration
测量和绘画
Measurement and drawing
我们先来瞄一瞄measurement
let's have a look at measurement first.
在一个View被draw(在屏幕上绘制)之前.
before a view hierarchy can be drawn.
先要向Android framework确定measure的规格(~spec)
the first is to ask the Android framework is the measurement packs
此时,
in this step
所有的Views会按照在View层级结构中从上到下的次序被测量
All the views in the hierarchy will be measured top down
这意味着测量从root view 开始
meaning measure starts from the root view
在root view里,对它的孩子依次进行测量
and track through each child view
也就是调用孩子节点的onMeasure()方法
each view receives a call onMeasure()
这就是父节点要求子节点更新其measure的时机
when its parent requests that update its measure size
子节点自行measure其大小
it's the responsibility of each view to set its own size
根据父节点提供的约束条件
based on the constrain given by the parent
调用setMeasureDimension()来存储测量的结果
and store those measurements by calling setMeasureDimension()
不调用setMeasureDimension()的话,会导致异常
forgetting to do this will result an exception
每个视图在onMeasure()的时候,会传入两个复合型int值
each view is given two packed int values onMeasure()
这两个值被称作"测量规格"
these are called measure specs
view应该根据这两个spec进行一些检查
and there is something that a view should inspect
来决定自身的大小
to determine how to set its size
一个measure spec很简单就是一个表示大小的值
a measure spec is simply a size value
它的高(16)位表示了Mode标识
with a mode flag encoded into its high order bits
Mode有3种
there are three possible
values for a spec mode
不确定,至多,以及精确
UNSPECIFIED , AT MOST , and EXACTLY
不确定mode:view可以被设置为任意大小
UNSPECIFIED tells the view to set its dimensions to any desired size
至多:就是view大小不能超过给定值
AT MOST ...any size less than or equal to the given spec
准确mode:就是View只能设置为给定的大小
EXACTLY ...on to the size given
看,哥来教你一手.
this is a helper utility here
我经常拿这个方法来快速测量大多自定义视图的大小
that i often use to quickly size most custom views
因为哥这招在大多数情况下都挺管用
as it provides general behaviors needed in most situations
当用wrap content设置宽高的时候,
it may also be important to provide measurements
如果能提供一个测量的方法,来求出目标的宽高.
of what your desire size is
就显得比较重要了.
for situations where wrap content will be used to layout the view
这个方法就是我们用来计算我们
here is the method we used to compute the desired width
自定义视图的目标宽度的.
for our custom view example.
我们先取到自定义视图里面的3个元素的宽度
we obtain width values for the three major elements in this view
由此返回自定义视图本身的所要求的宽度值
and return the space that will be required
用此值来draw重叠的logos以及文字说明
to draw the overlapping logos and text
与算宽度值类似
imilarly,
这个方法是算高度的
here is the method our example used to compute desired height value
这里的高度只与图片内容有关.
this is governed completely by the image content
因此,我们在这个方向上不用考虑
so we don't need to pay attention to
文本元素的内容.
the text element when measure in this direction
这有一个小贴士,
here is the tip to help keep you on the right track.
不要想太多,去花时间鼓捣你并不需要的东西.
don't spend time testing and overwriting states you don't need
你的自定义控件跟系统控件不同
unlike the framework widgets
你的控件只需满足你的需求就行(其他的事情交给framework)
your custom view only need to suit your application need
过于修补代码来处理
over optimizing the code to handle measurement states
那些不会出现的测量情形
that will never occur in your application
是浪费时间的表现
is a waste time of an effort
先找自定义View的父元素
please use custom view inside its final layout
对framework提供的measure spec进行检查
inspect the values the framework give you for measure specs
然后,写出针对特定情况的测量代码
and then build the measuring code to handle those specific cases
自定义视图的另一个主要作用是绘制自身的内容
a custom views other primary job is to draw its content
要做这个,你会从onDraw()方法中得到一个空白的canvas对象
for this you're given a blink canvas via onDraw() method
画布的大小和位置是根据你测量的view决定的
this canvas is sized and positioned according to your measured view
画布的初始坐标是其背后视图的(left,top)
so the origin matches up with the top left of the view back
画布里面有画形状,
canvas supports calls to draw shapes
颜色,文本,位图以及其他的方法
colors , text , bitmap and more
好多framework 组件,像
many framework components such as
画图的或者文本显示的,
drawable images and text layouts
都提供的自身的onDraw()方法
even provide their own draw methods to
直接在画布上渲染其内容
render their contents on to the canvas directly
在此例中,我们就利用了其自身画图的方法
which is what we have taken advantage of in this example
你可能也觉得,
you may find yourself
能在XML文件里面给自定义视图
wanting to provide attributes to your custom view
自定义一些属性值是蛮不错的
from with in the layout xml
我们可以通过在工程资源目录下
we accomplish this by declaring a style-able block
声明一个<style-able>标签来做到这点
in the project resources
标签里面必须包含自定义视图
this block must contain all the attributes
所需要的全部属性值
we would like to read from the layout xml
通常,
when possible ,
最有效的做法是重用
it is most efficient to reuse attributes
framework定义好的属性值.
already defined by the framework
看哥做的.
as we have done here
我们在<styleable>里面声明view所需要的属性值
we are utilizing an existing text and drawable attributes to
在布局文件中,用真实值来填充这些属性
feed in the content sources and text styling information
you should apply
在创建View的时候
during view creation
我们用 obtainStyledAttributes()这个方法
we use obtainStyledAttributes()
来提取在<styleab>中的属性名称
to extract the values of the attributes name in our styleleable block
此方法返回的是一个TypedArray
the method returned a typed array instance
遍历这个数组,就能得到不同数据类型的属性值
which allows us to retrieve each attribute as the appropriate type
管它是"画图","维度"或"颜色",都可以检索到
whether it be a drawable,dimension or color
记住
don't forget
TypedArray是个重量级的对象
TypedArrays are heavy weight objects
在你提取完所需的属性值后
and they should be recycled immediately
应该马上将其回收
after all the attributes you need have been exacted
现在,我们已经目睹了
now, we've seen how easy it is
写自定义view真的是很惬意啊
to build our own custom content into a view
那么,咱们能不能写过自定义的布局管理器呢
what about building a custom layout manager
像线性布局跟相对布局这样的控件
widgets like LinearLayout and RelativeLayout
其中管理子视图的代码量很大
have a lot of code in them to manage child views
那么,咱来干这事儿是不是有点牵强
so this must be really hard , right?
且别担心先,山人自有妙计.
well,hopefully ,this next example will convince you
看下一个例子吧
that this is not the case
这里,俺写了一个自己的ViewGroup
here we're going to building a view group
它将其所有子视图分配到3x3的等距网格中
that lays out all its child views with equal spacing in a 3x3 grid
这个效果也可用
the same effect could be accomplished by
线性布局套线性布局来做
nesting LinearLayout and inside LinearLayout(x2)
但这会使得布局的层级结构很深
creating a hierarchy many many levels deep
但是,
however
哥可以教你如何4两拨千斤
with just a little bit of effort
哥的妙计可以大大的收窄布局的层级结构
we can drastically flatten that hierarchy
从而获取很多的性能
into something much more performance
就跟	view差不多
just as with views,
ViewGroup们也要负责其自身的测量
view groups are responsible for measuring themselves
此例中,我们计算了ViewGroup的大小
for this example, we are computing the size of the view group
通过framework下的getDefaultSize()方法
using the framework getDefaultSize() method
此方法本质上依据"测量规格"返回测量大小
which essentially return the size provided by the measurespec
有一点例外
in all cases except
就是父视图的宽高是固定时
when exact size requirement is expose by the parent
ViewGroup在测量时比View多做了一件事
ViewGroups has one more job doing measurement though
它必须通知它的子视图去测量其自身的宽高
it must also tell all its child views to measure themselves
我们要做的是让每个孩子视图的宽高
we want to have each view take a bit exactly 1/3
只取到父视图宽高的1/3
of both container's height and width
我们构造了一个新的measurespec来做这事儿
this is done by constructing a new measure spec
其组成包括:经计算的view的大小(父1/3)
with a computed fraction of the view size
和EXACTLY标识的模式
and the mode flag set to EXACTLY
这会使得每个子视图
this will notify each child view
必须测量到的宽高必须是
that they must be measured to exactly the size
我们指定的精确宽高
we are giving them
我们要命令每个子视图都这么做
one method of dispatching these commands
我们可以调用每个孩子的onMeasure()方法
is to call measure on every child view
除此之外,在ViewGroup里面还有个帮助者方法
but there are also helper methods inside ViewGroup
可以使这个过程简化
to simplify this process
在这里,我们调用的了measureChildren()
in our example here,we are calling measure children
这使所有子视图都用相同的测量规格
which applies the same spec to every child view
做完以上的后,我们还要设置自己的维度(宽高)
of course,we are still require to mark our own dimension,as well
通过调用setMeasureDimension来完成
via setMeasuredDimension() before returning
搞定了测量之后
after measurement
ViewGroup也要对其子视图
ViewGroups are also responsible
的位置宽高做界定
for setting the bounds of their child views
这事儿由onLayout()回调来干
though the onLayout() callback
由于网格大小是固定的,哥这代码不言自明
with our fixed size grid,this is pretty straight forward
我们基于索引来求出
we first determine based on index
每个子视图所在的行列号
which row's and column's view is in.
之后调用子视图的layout()方法
we can then call layout on the child
并指定其左,上,宽,高参数
and we can set its left,right,top and bottom position values
注意,在layout中,用了getMeasuredWidth()来求宽度
notice that inside layout  we can the getMeasureWidth()
getMeasureHeight()求高度
and getMeasuredHeight() methods on the view as well
此时的这些函数是有效的
these will always be validate at the stage
因为测量是在布局之前完成的
since the measurement pass comes before layout
这是个很方便的办法
and this is the handy way
来设置每个子视图的边界
to set the bounding box of each child view
另一个小贴士哦
here is another tip
测量和布局
measurement and layout
好不好用取决于你的实现
can be a simple or complex as you make it
当你尝试处理每一个
it is easy to get lost
可能影响子视图布局的配置变化时,
attempting to handle every possible configuration change
你会迷失方向.
that may effect how you layout child views
坚持去写这样的代码
stick to writing code
只处理那些程序中的确会出现的情况
the cases your application will actually encounter
尽管视图组通常不会画自身的内容
while ViewGroups don't generally draw any content of there own
但是在很多情况下还是有这个需求的
there are many situations where this could be useful
有两个地方,
there are helpful instances
我们可以要求ViewGroup画一些内容
where we can ask ViewGroup to do some drawing
一个是在dispatchDraw()里,父类的方法调用之后
the first is inside dispatchDraw() after super has been called
此时,由于孩子视图已经绘制完毕
at this stage,child views have already been drawn
因此我们所画的东西就会在其之上
and we have an opportunity to do additional drawing on top
在我们的例子中
in our example
我们利用这点绘制的网格的分割线
we are leveraging this to draw grid lines over our box view
第二个地方是ViewGroup的onDraw()回调
the second is using the same onDraw() callback
正如之前我们在View里见到的onDraw一样
as we saw before was view
我们在这儿画的东西会赶在孩子视图绘制之前
anything we draw here will be drawn before the child views
所以这里的内容是在孩子视图内容之下的
and thus will show us underneath them
这里适合画各种
this can be helpful for drawing any type
动态的背景或者是一些状态选择器
of dynamic backgrounds or selector states
如果你要在ViewGroup的onDraw里面添代码
if you wish to put code into the onDraw() of a ViewGroup
你不能忘记使ViewGroup的onDraw回调有效
you must also remember to enable drawing callbacks
调用setWillNotDraw(false)
was setWillNotDraw() false
否则,你的onDraw()方法不能被触发
otherwise,your own onDraw() method will never be triggered
因为ViewGroup自身onDraw方法默认是禁用的
this is because ViewGroup by default has self drawing disabled
咱们回头再看看属性吧
so back to attributes for a minute
如果我们想要填充的属性
what if attributes we want to feed into the View
并不存在到平台上怎么办
don't already exist in the platform
这会使得重用一个属性(未预定义)变得很笨拙
it would be awkward to trying reuse one for a different purpose
解决办法还是有的
while in that case
我们可以在styleable中自定义属性
we can define custom attributes inside our styleable block
不同之处仅仅在于
the only different here is that
我们必须定义好其代表的数据类型
we must also define the type of data that attribute represent
这些数据类型都是系统定义好的
something we didn't need to do for the framework
我们只管拿来用
since it already has them pre defined
这里我们定义了一个维度属性和颜色属性
here,we are defining a dimension and a color attribute
通过XML文件给分割线自定义了样式
to provide the styling for the boxes grid lines via XML
现在,我们可以在布局内部应用自定义的属性了
now, we can apply this attributes externally in our layouts
要注意的是,属性是定义在我们程序包下的
notice that attributes defined in our own application package
这需要一个指向APK内部资源的命名空间
require a separate namespace that points to our internal APK resources
同样要注意,自定义的布局跟
notice also that our custom layout behavior no differently
framework定义的其他控件没有两样
than the other layout widgets in the framework
我们可以直接在XML文件中
we can simply add child views to it directly
为其添加子视图
through the XML layout file
乐者为王(-_^)
just for fun
我们可以把layout用include包含进来
we will even include the layout inside itself
来创建整个9x9的效果
to create the full 9x9 effect
正如你之前看到的
that you saw in the earlier screenshot
我们也定义了一个有点假的分割线
we have also defined a slightly faker grid separator
用于区分主要的区块和次要的区块
to distinguish the major blocks from the minor blocks
哥希望你真的懂了
i hope that now you can see how simple it is
去写自定义视图跟布局不难
to get started building custom views and layouts
减少对框架控件的依赖
reduce dependence on the framework widgets
可以提升用户体验,以及优化视图层级结构
leads to better user interfaces and less clutter in your view hierarchy
你的用户跟设备都会感谢这点
your users and your devices will thank you for it
一定要上github去看哥的源码啊
be sure to visit Github link to find full example showing here
里面除了有完整的实例还有些其他的
as well as others
相信可以对你写自定义view有所帮助
to help you comfortable building custom views
感谢大家肯花时间听讲.我希望你学到了一些新东西
thanks you for you time today and i hope you learn something new
如果觉得视频不错,请推荐给更多的人
如有翻译错误,请留言指出,本人不胜感激
BLOG:http://blog.2qwe.com
新浪微博:http://weibo.com/2802042662 Ocean-藏心